<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>stmu.co</title>
    <description>focussed on typography, minimal design and
 quality photography built using the Jekyll platform.
</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2020 14:41:02 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2020 14:41:02 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quote review: trillion dollar coach</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In general, I thought this was an ok book. Let’s give it a 7/10. 
The tips / tricks / approaches seem pretty well known nowadays. 
Maybe it was different a while ago, when Bill started out.
The big thing, it seems to me, isn’t to know all the tips/tricks, but to be able to know when to apply them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B076ZHG3H3/ref=cm_sw_em_r_mt_dp_U_vTUXCbR8BARYT&quot;&gt;Trillion dollar coach&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Schmidt  (Author), Jonathan Rosenberg (Author), Alan Eagle (Author).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting quotes from the book:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Bill&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bill had been a big shot at Apple, VP of sales and marketing, and had been very successful at Kodak. In both companies he had been detail oriented, frequently micromanaging his team members. That worked pretty well, so when he took on the CEO role at Claris, he figured it was his job to tell everyone what to do. Which he did. Late one afternoon Donna dropped by Bill’s office and told him that if he was going to tell everyone what to do, they were all going to quit and go back to Apple. No one wanted to work for a dictator. She added a bit more wisdom for the first-time CEO: “Bill, your title makes you a manager; your people make you a leader.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is being discussed in a weekly coaching session&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So when we met Bill in our weekly coaching sessions, what we discussed first and foremost was management: operations and tactics. Bill rarely weighed in on strategic issues, and if he did, it was usually to make sure that there was a strong operating plan to accompany the strategy. What were the current crises? How quickly were we going to manage our way out of them? How was hiring going? How were we developing our teams? How were our staff meetings going? Were we getting input from everyone? What was being said, what wasn’t being said? He cared that the company was well run, and that we were improving as managers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;various-beliefs&quot;&gt;Various beliefs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The most important asset”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People are the foundation of any company’s success. The primary job of each manager is to help people be more effective in their job and to grow and develop. We have great people who want to do well, are capable of doing great things, and come to work fired up to do them. Great people flourish in an environment that liberates and amplifies that energy. Managers create this environment through support, respect, and trust. Support means giving people the tools, information, training, and coaching they need to succeed. It means continuous effort to develop people’s skills. Great managers help people excel and grow. Respect means understanding people’s unique career goals and being sensitive to their life choices. It means helping people achieve these career goals in a way that’s consistent with the needs of the company. Trust means freeing people to do their jobs and to make decisions. It means knowing people want to do well and believing that they will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;TO BUILD RAPPORT AND BETTER RELATIONSHIPS AMONG TEAM MEMBERS, START TEAM MEETINGS WITH TRIP REPORTS, OR OTHER TYPES OF MORE PERSONAL, NON-BUSINESS TOPICS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Remember, he believed the most important thing a manager does is to help people be more effective and to grow and develop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HAVE A STRUCTURE FOR 1:1s, AND TAKE THE TIME TO PREPARE FOR THEM, AS THEY ARE THE BEST WAY TO HELP PEOPLE BE MORE EFFECTIVE AND TO GROW.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;DEFINE THE “FIRST PRINCIPLES” FOR THE SITUATION, THE IMMUTABLE TRUTHS THAT ARE THE FOUNDATION FOR THE COMPANY OR PRODUCT, AND HELP GUIDE THE DECISION FROM THOSE PRINCIPLES.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On managing the abberant genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Support them as they continue to perform, and minimize time spent fighting them. Instead, invest that energy in trying as hard as possible to coach them past their aberrant behavior. As long as you can do this successfully, the rewards can be tremendous: more genius, less aberrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;ABERRANT GENIUSES—HIGH-PERFORMING BUT DIFFICULT TEAM MEMBERS—SHOULD BE TOLERATED AND EVEN PROTECTED, AS LONG AS THEIR BEHAVIOR ISN’T UNETHICAL OR ABUSIVE AND THEIR VALUE OUTWEIGHS THE TOLL THEIR BEHAVIOR TAKES ON MANAGEMENT, COLLEAGUES, AND TEAMS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;COMPENSATING PEOPLE WELL DEMONSTRATES LOVE AND RESPECT AND TIES THEM STRONGLY TO THE GOALS OF THE COMPANY.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The purpose of a company is to take the vision you have of the product and bring it to life,” he said once at a conference. “Then you put all the other components around it—finance, sales, marketing—to get the product out the door and make sure it’s successful.” This was not the way things were done in Silicon Valley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This was a constant theme from Bill and something he preached to us and others: if you have the right product for the right market at the right time, go as fast as you can. There are minor things that will go wrong and you have to fix them quickly, but speed is essential. This means that finance, sales, or marketing shouldn’t tell the product teams what to do. Instead, these groups can supply intelligence on what customer problems need solving, and what opportunities they see. They describe the market part of “product market fit.” Then they stand by, let the product teams work, and clear the way of things that might slow them down. As Bill often commented, “Why is marketing losing its clout? Because it forgot its first name: product.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hesitate this here, because I think some people will fire someone way to early. Generally, those people will also think of themselves as being rather patient and too slow to fire. They might take the advice below to heart, but really shouldn’t. So, if you read the quote below and immediately agree, the advice is not for you…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“When you fire someone, you feel terrible for about a day, then you say to yourself that you should have done it sooner. No one ever succeeds at their third chance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;IF YOU HAVE TO LET PEOPLE GO, BE GENEROUS, TREAT THEM WELL, AND CELEBRATE THEIR ACCOMPLISHMENTS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On managing the board&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bill’s perspective on boards starts with this observation: the CEO manages the board and board meetings, not the other way around.Board meetings fail when the CEO doesn’t own and follow her agenda. That agenda should always start with operational updates: the board needs to know how the company is doing. That includes financial and sales reports, product status, and metrics around operational rigor (hiring, communications, marketing, support). If the board has committees, for example to oversee audit and finance or compensation, have those committees meet ahead of time (in person or via phone or video conference) and present updates at the board meeting. The first order of business always needs to be a frank, open, succinct discussion about how the company is performing. Much of this material can be sent to board members ahead of time, with the idea that they will review it and be up-to-date on most stuff when they come to the meeting. If you throw a full set of financial reports up on a screen in a board meeting, they will want to talk about it forever, and you end up getting bogged down in operational details that probably don’t need the board’s attention. Send out financial and other operational details ahead of time and expect board members to review them and come with questions. And when we say expect, we mean expect: board members who don’t do their homework shouldn’t stick around. Dan Rosensweig once had a guy on his board at Chegg who wouldn’t read anything ahead of the board meeting and then spent a lot of time at the meeting asking about details that were in his preread. At one board meeting, Dan got angry at him for wasting everyone’s time. Afterward, Bill, who was at the meeting, told Dan that he shouldn’t lose his cool like that. Send the guy an information packet a week ahead of time and tell him exactly which pages you are going to cover in the meeting and exactly what you expect him to do. So that’s what Dan did. And the same thing happened: the guy showed up unprepared and wasted a lot of time asking questions about things he should have known already. Yeah, I was wrong, Bill told Dan afterward. Fire him. In our board meetings at Google, Bill always pushed Eric to ensure that the operations review included a thorough set of highlights and lowlights. Here’s what we did well and what we’re proud of; here’s what we didn’t do so well. The highlights were always easy to compile; teams love dressing up their best successes and presenting them to the board. But the lowlights, not so much. It can take some prodding to make teams be completely frank about where they are falling short, and indeed, Eric often rejected an initial draft of the board lowlights for not being honest enough. He was dogged in ensuring that the lowlights were authentic, and as a result, the board would see the bad news along with the good. Creating a robust set of real lowlights might entail giving honest updates on things ranging from revenue growth and product limitations to employee attrition and concerns about the pace of innovation. A 2002 Harvard Business Review article notes that a “virtuous cycle of respect, trust, and candor” is one thing that makes “great boards great.”24 And this level of honesty sets a tone of transparency and honesty that reverberates throughout the company. A company that is honest with its board can be honest with itself, too; people learn that not only is it okay to frankly share bad news, it’s expected. Determining lowlights is an important task, something to be handled by people running the business, not left to support functions such as finance or communications. At Google, we had product managers handle the task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Who should be on the board? Smart people with good business expertise who care deeply about the company and are genuinely interested in helping and supporting the CEO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the coaching method&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How did Bill do it? First, he only coached the coachable. Then, if you passed that test, he listened intently, practiced complete candor, believed that his coachees could achieve remarkable things, and was intensely loyal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In a coaching session with Bill, you could expect that he would listen intently. No checking his phone for texts or email, no glancing at his watch or out the window while his mind wandered. He was always right there. Today it is popular to talk about “being present” or “in the moment.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“mundane, almost trivial” things like listening and chatting with employees are important aspects of successful leadership, because “people feel more respected, visible and less anonymous, and included in teamwork.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An important component of providing candid feedback is not to wait. “A coach coaches in the moment,” Scott Cook says. “It’s more real and more authentic, but so many leaders shy away from that.” Many managers wait until performance reviews to provide feedback, which is often too little, too late. Bill’s feedback was in the moment (or very close to it), task specific, and always followed by a grin and a hug, all of which helped remove the sting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t tell people what to do, tell them stories about why they are doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He notes in an email to us that “we often feel torn between supporting and challenging others. Social scientists reach the same conclusion for leadership as they do for parenting: it’s a false dichotomy. You want to be supportive and demanding, holding high standards and expectations but giving the encouragement necessary to reach them. Basically, it’s tough love. Disagreeable givers are gruff and tough on the surface, but underneath they have others’ best interests at heart. They give the critical feedback no one wants to hear but everyone needs to hear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bill’s perspective was that it’s a manager’s job to push the team to be more courageous. Courage is hard. People are naturally afraid of taking risks for fear of failure. It’s the manager’s job to push them past their reticence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;PEOPLE ARE MOST EFFECTIVE WHEN THEY CAN BE COMPLETELY THEMSELVES AND BRING THEIR FULL IDENTITY TO WORK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;WHEN FACED WITH A PROBLEM OR OPPORTUNITY, THE FIRST STEP IS TO ENSURE THE RIGHT TEAM IS IN PLACE AND WORKING ON IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;THE TOP CHARACTERISTICS TO LOOK FOR ARE SMARTS AND HEARTS: THE ABILITY TO LEARN FAST, A WILLINGNESS TO WORK HARD, INTEGRITY, GRIT, EMPATHY, AND A TEAM-FIRST ATTITUDE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair people on projects&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The deliverable matters, but what matters just as much is the opportunity for the pair of teammates to work together on something and get to know and trust each other. That is invaluable to the team’s success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;TO CARE ABOUT PEOPLE YOU HAVE TO CARE ABOUT PEOPLE: ASK ABOUT THEIR LIVES OUTSIDE OF WORK, UNDERSTAND THEIR FAMILIES, AND WHEN THINGS GET ROUGH, SHOW UP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Once you have your team or your community, what matters most are the bonds between the people on the team, which are forged by caring for each other and the common good. With all the trips Bill took with people, the trips were not the goal of the communities, the communities were the goal of the trips. It was all about making enduring connections between people,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping people - pay it forward&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Most of the time, these little gifts were what Adam Grant, crediting businessman Adam Rifkin in his book Give and Take, calls “five-minute favors.” They are easy for the person doing the favor, requiring minimal personal cost, but mean a lot to the recipient.7 Grant also notes, in a 2017 article written with Reb Rebele, that “being an effective giver isn’t about dropping everything every time for every person. It’s about making sure that the benefits of helping others outweigh the costs to you.” People who do this well are “self-protective givers.” They are “generous, but they know their limits. Instead of saying yes to every request for help, they look for high-impact, low-cost ways of giving so that they can sustain their generosity—and enjoy it along the way.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HOLD A SPECIAL REVERENCE FOR—AND PROTECT—THE PEOPLE WITH THE MOST VISION AND PASSION FOR THE COMPANY.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2019 10:30:37 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>/trillion-dollar-coach.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/trillion-dollar-coach.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>book-highlights</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Highlights from the book: Finding my virginity - Richard Branson</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Richard Branson is managing to lead a life completely in line with his own internal values. Or at least, that’s how he tells it.
“Finding my virginity” is a wonderful book from a chap in love with life and adventure.
It is a testament to daring to be your own uncompromising, quirky self, instead of trying to fit in the image of the consummate professional. 
Even if you’re not sure this approach will work, it’s sure a lot more fun to live this way!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few (lot) of quotes and highlights below, for your enjoyment and my reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-trying-to-find-talent-and-ideas-everywhere&quot;&gt;On trying to find talent and ideas everywhere&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spotting someone with potential and the same values as Richard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Brett was a great example. I’d first spotted his potential when he wrote an excellent note to a group of new starters. I began following his progress closely, and saw how he dealt with people in a personable manner and got the best out of them. He was someone who understood the little details of the airline industry that make all the difference; he knew management had to be accessible and visible, so would often get out and about, even rolling his sleeves up with the baggage handlers to heave bags and hear their issues from the front line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard wanted to offer Brett a new job. It didn’t go as planned however:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;‘I really appreciate the offer,’ he explained, ‘but I’ve got two young kids now, and my wife and I have decided to move back to Australia.’ I was disappointed, but accepted his reasoning. ‘I always respect a person who puts family first,’ I told him. Wishing him all the best, I added: ‘If you want to do anything in Australia, let me know and we’ll see what we can do.’ There was a pause. ‘Funny you should say that,’ he replied. ‘I’ve had an idea for a few years now that I’d love you to hear.’ I always like someone ready to seize their chance. ‘OK,’ I said. ‘What is it?’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Brett’s plan was delivered to my door the next morning. I’ve always liked people who move fast too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valuing &lt;em&gt;values&lt;/em&gt; over experience. To me, this also equals looking for talent where others won’t look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Rather than going for experience we wanted to recruit people who wouldn’t usually apply for airline jobs. Virgin has always focused on finding the best possible people, and I was determined to set our new airline apart by having the finest staff in the world. We didn’t want people who had been working at airlines for years – we needed fresh faces with new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;starting-and-running-a-new-business&quot;&gt;Starting (and running) a new business&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richards approach when thinking about a new idea is not to start it himself, but find the people that can run it better than he can. Although, he’s able to do that now, he did run many businesses himself in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As with any other business, I started to search around for people to make it happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;what I am good at: finding markets that need shaking up, coming up with ways to make people’s lives better, then finding brilliant people to bring it to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the businesses are pretty much the same: they deliver some service and try to do it better, with better customer service and less dull. It works because people respond to humanity and who doesn’t like to laugh once in a while?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Virgin Active is one company that closely mirrors my vision for the whole Virgin brand. It is all about improving people’s lives, has a spirit of fun and entrepreneurship at its heart, and is committed to giving staff and customers the best possible time. The way it has been run, from a boot-strap start-up into a global business, is the perfect example of delegation and trust. By letting them make their own mistakes and enjoy their own triumphs – chipping in whenever necessary, instead of being on the phone every day second-guessing their decisions – Matthew, Frank and the team have grown a worldwide brand people love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But being able to see the bigger picture is what has enabled me to move into so many different sectors. Most business leaders want to oversee every single part of their operation. I hone in on what is important. This can be tiny details, not just over-arching strategy. Either way, I find brilliant people like Will, I delegate and let them get on with it. I am able to let go, when other people can’t. As shareholder, I delegate to management teams who take strategic decisions to drive our business forward. But I can also be as stubborn as hell when I believe in an idea and those same brilliant people around me do not. I have learned that my mind works in different ways to many others. If I had to name a skill I possess, it would be lateral thinking. When all logic is pointing in one direction, but it just doesn’t make sense to me, I question it. ‘Forgive me, it’s probably my dyslexia,’ I will begin, or ‘Sorry, I’m probably being foolish, but I don’t quite follow you.’ Then I will ask seemingly obvious questions, which don’t always result in the answers I expect. Out of this inquisitiveness, companies are sometimes born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A crisis is a moment where many opportunities pop up. If you’ve put yourself in a good position in the fat years, you’ll be able to take advantage of those opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A crisis is often a good time to start a new business. When the 2007 economic downturn happened, I thought it would be the perfect moment to begin searching for suitable properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I try to simplify everything and apply this to every aspect of my life, however small or big. This means paying attention to detail. A good entrepreneur signs every cheque personally, say, every quarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then there are bigger amounts. Each year our banks required us to undertake a valuation exercise on some Virgin Group assets, apparently as part of their internal policies but for no clear reason, taking substantial time and costing us over $100,000 a year. One call and they agreed that they didn’t actually need this. For every dollar you save today, the cumulative effect is enormous. Too often people only look into these details when times are tight and they are losing money. It is much easier to remove unnecessary over-complications and costs when business is doing well, keeping your company lean and mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Like most good ideas, it is an artful solution to a complex problem. As I tell every young entrepreneur I meet asking for tips: keep it simple, stupid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some people, delegating comes naturally. For others (like me), it’s difficult. For everyone, it seems to be necessary…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My first widely read blog, in early 2010, was about the art of delegation. It was an appropriate theme since delegation has been a secret of my success for five decades. Asking for support is a strength, not a weakness. If you try to do everything yourself, you won’t succeed and will make yourself miserable along the way. As a dyslexic, things like spelling and grammar have never come naturally to me. Rather than waste time pondering the difference between ‘there’, ‘they’re’ and ‘their’, I find talented people to collaborate with and delegate to. I now work with Greg Rose and our content team on around 600 blogs per year, and call the team several times a day (and night!). If you think that sounds too time-consuming, think of all the things you do that take lots of time and are not productive. Rather than slave over a spreadsheet, why not write a blog and turn your pitch into a story? Humans communicate through stories; it’s how we make sense of our surroundings, ourselves and our place in the world. As the writer Lawrence Weschler said in The New New Journalism: ‘Human beings have glands that secrete all sorts of things. But the human mind secretes stories. We live narratives. That is the only way we know how to experience anything, and it is our glory.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-staying-true-to-yourself-and-what-feels-right&quot;&gt;On staying true to yourself and what feels right&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that I think people are not doing enough: if you have the capacity to build something, why not use it to build things that make you happy.
Not everything has to be a cold, mathematical ROI calculation. We are human after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Looking back, I think most people would have taken the money. Certainly, everyone at Virgin Group wanted to – it would have been an extraordinary return on investment. But emotionally – and I do most things on emotion – it would have felt like selling one’s own child. Staying at the Holiday Inn at Potts Point with all the cabin crew certainly influenced me. They were such a delightful, fun team. In the end, the idea of selling them out was just too strange. It felt fitting that the company which started over a few beers was saved by a conversation over a few more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;approach-to-marketing&quot;&gt;Approach to marketing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Branson has been in the media many times and it is easy to understand this is at least partly marketing.
The impressive part is that he has managed to portray an image that fits with the way he aspires to lead (at least part of) his life.
Fun fact, while it doesn’t seem that way now, he was originally not comfortable with putting the spotlight on him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ever since my mentor Sir Freddie Laker showed me the benefits of leaders being the visible fronts of businesses, I’ve been comfortable with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-family&quot;&gt;On family&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much to add: if someone with x businesses can make time for family, everyone can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was debating the role of women in business in front of thousands of people at an event organised by Maria Shriver in California. Although it was a big deal, family always comes first, no matter what, which is why I answered the phone to hear her results. When Holly rang, I had asked the audience to bear with me as I took the call, and they were happy to play along with it. ‘Hang on one second. I want to tell them your results.’ I quickly relayed the good news and the crowd gave her a standing ovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Despite Holly enjoying her role, I still had an inkling that she might like to join Virgin at some point. After all, we have always been a family business. I genuinely felt that Holly could achieve more and make a bigger positive impact in the world working under the Virgin umbrella; she could use her medical experience, but working with greater financial resources and variously skilled teams of people to make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(this one also is about the difference between being an expert and using money, connections, multiple experts to have a broader impact)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As is my usual way on family time, I ignored the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When Joan and I had children I was determined to be there with them as much as possible, which is why I always worked from home, first on our houseboat and then in Holland Park. But I was still away a fair amount with work. Now, with our&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;negotiating&quot;&gt;Negotiating&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shrewd negotiating? Not always. Sometimes, it’s just about making sure the other party understands you really want a thing to happen. 
While I do think you should be adequately compensated for your work, we shouldn’t kill a deal that has the potential to benefit everyone because we think we’re “worth more”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When it comes to deals like this, or any negotiations really, the key is to display passion, know-how and determination. Get to the point quickly, be persistent and consistent, and don’t rely too heavily on prompts, statistics, and certainly not PowerPoint slides. I went into the meeting with my notebook in my back pocket, armed with beautiful spaceship pictures, a lot of enthusiasm and belief in the project. Investors buy into people and ideas, not numbers alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then, in March 2018, I received a WhatsApp message from the Crown Prince confirming his commitment to the partnership. He was visiting the Queen and the Prime Minister in London, and wanted to meet up with me. On my flight to England, I decided to sit down with all the details in front of me and write a letter to the Crown Prince’s key adviser, PIF CEO Yasir bin Othman Al-Rumayyan. I set out the history and explained our concerns about how the negotiations were going. I thought through the deal from both points of view and tried to come up with a really fair compromise that worked for both parties. Then I gave a list of seven key points which we needed to agree to close the deal. ‘I really hope that the above works for you and we can shake hands on it today,’ I wrote. ‘Anyway very much look forward to seeing you for breakfast. Best, Richard.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gathering-your-thoughts&quot;&gt;Gathering your thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thing is, we’re always going to be as busy as we allow ourselves to be. 
The real question is: are we as effective as we hope we are? Not thinking about the end goals or having to rework are absolute killers of ideas and projects.
Find a system that works for you and stick to it. 
And above all: make sure you have the time to think things through and write it down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People also often question how I find the time to write so regularly; whether notes, letters, blogs, op-eds, or even books like this. But the reality is I’m always getting my thoughts down on paper. The trick is to make it part of your daily routine. You have time to eat, drink, brush your teeth and do dozens of other things every day – just add writing to the list. I jot down ideas, thoughts, requests, reminders and doodles every single day; if I didn’t, I would forget them before I could ever put them into action. It doesn’t matter if you use a notebook and pen like me, or a shiny new tablet like Holly – the key is making writing a welcome habit. But keep a little pad in your back pocket just in case – you never have to charge a notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Making lists is both a way of remembering things and of ticking off achievements to mark progress. Without notes and follow-ups, chances are nothing would get done. I have met one particular government minister many times who never takes notes; he agrees on things and nothing happens. Another minister I know always takes notes, follows up and gets things done. If somebody works for me and doesn’t take notes, I ask them: ‘Are you too important? Note taking isn’t beneath anyone.’ I take notes in every meeting, to keep the frame of mind to learn. I edit as I go along, and follow up with dates and tasks in order of importance. I couldn’t have written two autobiographies without them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;general-shenanigans&quot;&gt;General shenanigans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mindset is the thing! :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I became the lease holder of our former London property the Roof Gardens after a bouncer refused me entry for wearing jeans and looking too scruffy. I bought the place the next day, and gently informed the bouncer to let me in regardless of my clothing. He turned out to be a delightful gentleman and ended up working for us for another three decades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hunter S. Thompson: ‘Life should not be a journey to the grave with the intention of arriving safely in a pretty and well preserved body, but rather to skid in broadside in a cloud of smoke, thoroughly used up, totally worn out, and loudly proclaiming “Wow! What a ride!”’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The next day we got back on the saddle for the final stretch of the cycling leg: riding to the toe of Italy. It was a fascinating and picturesque journey, which, thankfully, wasn’t as physically gruelling as the day before. However, having already hiked seventy kilometres and ridden nearly 2,000 kilometres, my body felt fit but completely worn out. With just two hours to go to the finish line, Sam overtook me. As he passed, something stirred inside me and I got a burst of energy. For the rest of the leg I rode flat-out as fast as I could, whooping like a schoolboy. Developing mental toughness isn’t just about being resilient – it’s about accessing your reserve tank when you think you just can’t go any further. At that moment, so close to the end and challenged by my son, I felt my reserve kick in. It’s something that I’ve relied on a lot in life, and have had to access on many occasions in business. In the dark moments we all have the power to pull ourselves up to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Somebody said to me after Strive that there are three stages to life: youth, middle age, and ‘you’re looking well’! Sadly, it’s probably true. I found myself getting more ‘you’re looking well’ comments than usual after Strive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2018 09:30:37 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/finding-my-virginity.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/finding-my-virginity.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>book-highlights</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes on the legitimate interest guide</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This article contains notes on the Working Party 29 opinion on the “Notion of legitimate interests of the data controller”. 
The full article can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://collections.internetmemory.org/haeu/20171122154227/http://ec.europa.eu/justice/data-protection/article-29/documentation/opinion-recommendation/files/2014/wp217_en.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-concept-of-interest&quot;&gt;The concept of interest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interest vs purpose:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Purpose: specific reason for processing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest: broader, the benefit the controller derives from processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example: interest is employee safety, purpose: implementation of access control&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interest must be pursued by the controller: so it is a real and present interest&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-is-an-interest-legitimate&quot;&gt;When is an interest legitimate?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interest can be considered as legitimate as long as the controller can pursue this interest in a way that is in accordance with data protection and other laws. In other words, a legitimate interest must be ‘acceptable under the law’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it needs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lawful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clearly articulated (to be able to conduct balancing test)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Present a real and present interest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-interests-or-rights-of-data-subject&quot;&gt;The interests or rights of data subject&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Must be given broad interpretation.
The interest of the data subject does not have to be “legitimate” (unlike controller interest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introducing-balancing-test&quot;&gt;Introducing balancing test&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interests and rights of subject and legitimate interests controller can be seen on a spectrum, ranging from very important to trivial.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Minor controller legitimate interest may only override even more trivial interests data subject&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Important legitimate interest may in some cases (subject to safeguards &amp;amp; measures) justify significant impact on rights and interests data subject&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-factors-for-balancing-test&quot;&gt;Key factors for balancing test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These factors can be taken into account when conducting a balancing test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;assessing-the-controllers-legitimate-interest&quot;&gt;Assessing the controllers legitimate interest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exercising a fundamental right (newspaper publicizing the details of fraudulent actions of a politician)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Public interest (wider community interest), for example: charity processing data for medical research, company detecting fraud (both for itself and the community)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other legitimate interest…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also playing a role in establishing legitimacy:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Non binding industry guidelines (or authority guidelines)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Societal expectations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impact-on-data-subjects&quot;&gt;Impact on data subjects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;assessing-impact&quot;&gt;Assessing impact:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both positive as negative impact into account&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also emotional impact (irritation, fear due to loss of control over data, realising data has been misused,…)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Impact’ =&amp;gt; covers any possible consequences of data processing (not only the ones that actually happened)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the sources of potential impact&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take normal risk assessment methodology into account (likelihood &amp;amp; severity)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;nature-of-data&quot;&gt;Nature of data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the more sensitive the information involved, the more consequences there may be for the data subject&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-way-the-data-is-processed&quot;&gt;The way the data is processed&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Processing scale: processing seemingly innocuous data on a large scale might lead to big impact&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The more negative or uncertain impact of processing is, the less it will be considered legitimate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;reasonable-expectations-of-data-subject&quot;&gt;Reasonable expectations of data subject&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is a data subject reasonably expecting the processing (like receiving email with product tips)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;status-controller-vs-data-subject&quot;&gt;Status controller vs data subject&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Controller might be dominant (very big company, the only provider,…)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If data subject is a child =&amp;gt; even more so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also important: employer ⇔ employee relationship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;provisional-balance&quot;&gt;Provisional balance&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Balance after taking into account the above interests and rights&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Might be clear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Might not be and need countermeasures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;additional-safeguards&quot;&gt;Additional safeguards&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If provisional balance not clear yes or no, we can introduce safeguards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examples:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Restriction of data collected&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Measures to ensure data cannot be used to take decisions on individuals&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Anonymisation techniques&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Increased transparency&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Right to opt out&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Other measures to empower data subject&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accountability-and-transparency&quot;&gt;Accountability and transparency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there a legitimate interest? Is the processing needed for the legitimate interest? Do interests and rights data subject override the legitimate interest? =&amp;gt; controller accountable for making and documenting exercise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using the processed data for something else than advertised is obviously not allowed (or even, only mentioned in the fine print)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-right-to-object&quot;&gt;The right to object&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even if we made the balancing test, data subject can still object -&amp;gt; need to assess if objection is legitimate and stop processing if so&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Controller can do more: offer unconditional opt out (is a additional safeguard)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Mar 2018 09:30:37 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/notes-gdpr-legitimate-interest.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/notes-gdpr-legitimate-interest.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>security</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reporting data breaches: GDPR requirements</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is what’s required from a data breach notification point-of-view:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the processor: you just have to inform your controller (so client in your case) “without undue delay” (so relatively quick). You only have to do this once you’ve come aware of a “personal data breach” (meaning, personal data is involved). You never directly communicate to the “data subject” (the person who’s data was lost), it’s the controller who has to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the controller: This one has been mentioned more often. You have to:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Report to the data protection authority (DPA) within 72 hours of becoming aware of the data breach, unless it’s unlikely to result in a risk to the “rights and freedoms of natural persons”. (this means, do report if there’s a chance. if you don’t report it, make sure to document why extremely well). The DPA for us is the privacy commission. Leaks can be reported here: https://www.privacycommission.be/fr/la-notification-de-fuites-de-donn%C3%A9es.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To the “data subject” (person who’s data was lost) if the breach is likely to result in a “high risk to the rights and freedoms of a natural person”, you need to report “without undue delay” and in an easy to understand language. There’s a loophole here: you don’t have to report anything if you take “subsequent measures which ensure that the risk is no longer likely to materialise”. (meaning: if you implement extra security measures, you don’t have to report to the subject). However, be aware that the DPA might force you to report a data breach.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 09:30:37 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/reporting-data-breach-for-gdpr.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/reporting-data-breach-for-gdpr.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>security</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What every developer should know about security</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This advice covers 80% of what I learned in half a decade as a pentester. 
Use it to your advantage (or don’t, that’s up to you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: this post is based on a ptacek comment on &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.ycombinator.com&quot;&gt;ycombinator&lt;/a&gt;.
I can’t find the comment anymore.
If you do, please let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;know-what-you-are-building&quot;&gt;Know what you are building&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems quite obvious, but I found it one of the biggest indicators of security: if the developers know the business domain and their tools, the hackers will be up against quite a challenge.
In my opinion, “quality” is directly tied to security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepare-for-disaster&quot;&gt;Prepare for disaster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pretty hard to be flawless all the time.
Related to the security domain: all your systems should be fully patched all the time, your code should not contain any bugs, your users should not give away their passwords,…
You get the message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s better to realise something will go wrong and have a good backup &amp;amp; restore plan:
Plan to update (or rebuild) your platform software at inconvenient times. Document and dry-run your update process, so you know it will work on no notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This became a lot easier recently, now that we have configuration managers and cloud providers. Use these, but make sure you have a plan for when the secrets to access your provider get stolen!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-sure-to-keep-an-eye-on-3rd-party-components&quot;&gt;Make sure to keep an eye on 3rd party components&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using libraries with known security issues is an open invitation to get hacked.
Put someone on your team in charge of tracking your dependencies and have a process by which you periodically check to make sure you’re capturing upstream security fixes.
There are some tools that can help you with this, here are two examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appcanary.com/&quot;&gt;App Canary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sourceclear.com/&quot;&gt;SourceClear&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-standard-cryptographic-options&quot;&gt;Use standard cryptographic options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use TLS to encrypt data in motion and use GPG to encrypt data at rest, and don’t do any other kind of crypto.
Don’t try to invent your own encryption scheme (unless you’re an expert in the field).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-your-code-boring&quot;&gt;Keep your code boring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay on your platform’s “golden path” for web security issues (meaning: use the functionality provided by the framework).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;watch-out-for-these-known-difficult-patterns&quot;&gt;Watch out for these known difficult patterns:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following pieces of functionality get a lot of attention from attackers and rightfully so.
They have proven themselves very difficult to implement correctly. 
Make sure to pay a lot of attention to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Triple check any piece of code that “shells out” to command line tools.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be wary of library code for web apps that includes “native” C/C++ code.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Triple-check code that handles direct file uploads and downloads. The file system introduces a new namespace, so upload/download code needs to juggle different privilege and authorization domains to handle it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pay-attention-to-the-trust-boundaries&quot;&gt;Pay attention to the trust boundaries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trust boundaries are areas where users suddenly are granted more rights (for example: the login mechanism).
By their nature, these are interesting to attackers. 
In the same vein as the advice in the previous point, make sure you pay a lot of attention to how they are implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, it’s a good idea to do administration out-of-band. Write a separate admin app (bonus: the admin app can look bad, and so is less expensive to maintain) that requires a VPN connection to access. Avoid special-privilege accounts in your normal apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;be-open-to-security-researchers&quot;&gt;Be open to security researchers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a security page. Have that page very cordially invite people to submit security flaws to an email address at your site; provide a PGP key for it. If you don’t have this page, you should know that you are inviting people to report security flaws to Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 09:30:37 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/what-everyone-should-know-about-security.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/what-everyone-should-know-about-security.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>security</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lightweight IT Security Policy for small and medium companies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Small and medium companies often have trouble to formulate what they expect from their employees with regards to security.
On the one hand, they often realise it’s important as information security is often in the news nowadays.
On the other hand, hiring expensive consultants is often overkill for these companies, as are the rigid security rules these consultants often like to introduce.
Being small and nimble is one of the main advantages of SME’s, so what’s needed is a pragmatic approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the advice I often give to clients that want to expand 20% effort to get 80% results. 
The right place to put these “rules” is somewhere you can refer to easily (ad valvas, on the intranet,…) and in the information package you provide to new hires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also a good idea to find someone in the team with a bit of an interest in security and officially make security a part of his or her role.
This person would then function as a point-of-contact for security related questions and help others, for example: to spot phishing attempts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-security-guidelines&quot;&gt;IT Security Guidelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above all, We’re counting on you to be responsible professionals and keep in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be aware that your computer is the key to your kingdom. It contains accounts where you’re authenticated, saved passwords, sensitive documents,… Make sure you take care of it appropriatly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look out for phishing emails. When something seems too good to be true, it often is. If possible, avoid clicking on any links in a suspicious email, not even to verify if the email is malicious. Instead, report suspeced email to “phishing@company.com” (an address you provide, managed by the security officer mentioned above). Learn more how to spot phishing on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.safeonweb.be&quot;&gt;safeonweb.be&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Please don’t reuse passwords. For example: don’t use the same password for LinkedIn as you use for your company accounts. Passwords often are stolen from public sites and the bad guys do try to use them for other accounts. Don’t make it easy for them! Additionally, use 2-factor authentication if possible (that means: if a site allows you to use a password and sends you a challenge via sms, please opt in to that).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can, use a password manager. Let it generate complex and different passwords for different services. By the way, did you know that “passphrases” are often better passwords than complex but shorter passwords? For example: “The Horse is Yellow!” is considered a better password than “xAbD45O”, it’s also easier to remember. Here’s a great explanation: &lt;img src=&quot;http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/password_strength.png&quot; alt=&quot;this&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enable full-disk encryption on computers and laptops. That way, when they are stolen or lost, criminals cannot read the content of your harddisk.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to avoid copying sensitive (or any) data to USB keys. These are too easy to lose, a lot of data has been leaked exactly like this. Instead, try to use other ways of sharing data like a common share internally or a password encrypted zip via a file-sharing website externally. If you do the latter, make sure to share the password via another channel (for example, sms).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep your computer up to date. Apply those updates and don’t use old, unsupported versions of software. Yes, those updates might be a pain sometimes, but there’s a reason they are created..&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On Windows (and Android), try to use antivirus software. Make sure to schedule a regular full scan (for example: once a week) and update the “virus signature” database regularly. The database is how the antivirus recognises new virusses, if hasn’t been updated, the newer virusses will still be able to get to you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any questions on security, concerns or to report a possible issue, contact the person you made responsible for security (see above).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lock your computers and devices when unattended, even for a minute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-note-about-wifi&quot;&gt;A note about wifi&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The office wifi is another weak point. Try to do at least the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check your router and make sure your wifi is encrypted with at least “WPA2” or “WPA-PSK”. “WEP” or “WPA1” (sometimes just called “WPA”) are unsecure methods of encryption, don’t use those.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be very careful with sharing the wifi password with visitors. Actually, I recommend never doing this. A better idea is to have a separate guest network for those visitors that do need internet access.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Choose a wifi password as described in point 4 above. If it helps, you can be a little silly, have fun with it, “Dave still has to bring birthday cake!” is perfectly valid!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t use Wi-Fi Protected Setup (WPS). There have been some serious security issues with it. This one is particularly tricky, as it’s enabled by default on many routers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;backups-backups-backups&quot;&gt;Backups, backups, backups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When things have gone wrong, having backups is a life saver! 
Alas, most of us don’t have any…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to assume for a moment that we’re all in agreement on the importance of backups.
There are 2 basic strategies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy your important files to a second storage. Pro: Quick, easy to restore one file. Con: you might miss some important documents and you might have to reinstall your operating system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make a copy of your whole hard disk. Pro: easy to restore from scratch. Con: it might take longer to take a backup.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both options are definitely better than having no backups. Whichever option you choose, it’s important that you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make backups regurarly (say, once a week). Make them part of your schedule to make sure you won’t forget.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the backup to storage that isn’t connected to your computer (ie: usb-drive) and store the storage somewhere safe. Making a backup to a connected network drive is not recommended, as there’s ransomware out there that will also destroy any files on connected drives. Dropbox, Google Drive and others are also vulnerable to this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you choose the second option, here are the steps to make a proper backup: &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/help/17127/windows-back-up-restore&quot;&gt;How to back up your computer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;helping-people-adhere-to-these-guidelines&quot;&gt;Helping people adhere to these guidelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to make sure these guidelines are followed is to explain why they matter. 
If they don’t know how to do everything, make sure to help them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it’s a good idea to prepare a small checklist to verify that people follow the guidelines.
Items like: “Do you have all updates installed?” and “Is your antivirus still up to date?” are good candidates for this list.
Periodically go around the office (say, once a month) with this list.
Try to act more like a coach than like a policeman.
When you find someone not following the rules, use the opportunity to again explain why they matter and help them to configure their systems correctly.
This will show you care and people won’t be afraid to approach you with their questions around security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-to-find-more-information&quot;&gt;Where to find more information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://decentsecurity.com/#/holiday-tasks/&quot;&gt;https://decentsecurity.com/#/holiday-tasks/&lt;/a&gt; : Tips on keeping your computer healthy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.safeonweb.be/nl&quot;&gt;https://www.safeonweb.be/nl&lt;/a&gt; : Various tips on staying secure online, geared towards a Belgian audience (Dutch/French)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/help/17127/windows-back-up-restore&quot;&gt;How to back up your computer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 09:30:37 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/security-policy-for-sme.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/security-policy-for-sme.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>summary</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Designing your life (Dave Evans, Bill Burnett)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Below are the 5 mindsets the authors introduce to use to design your life.
They struck a chord with me, so I put them here to ensure I would read them often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;curiosity&quot;&gt;Curiosity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes everything new, makes you try things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helps you to be one of those people that “knows how to get lucky”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bias-to-action&quot;&gt;Bias to action&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build your way forward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designers try many things, test often, until they find a solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reframing&quot;&gt;Reframing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Taking a step back, helps us get unstuck.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Makes sure we’re working on the right problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;awareness&quot;&gt;Awareness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Know it’s a process, don’t have to be perfect every time/all the time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helps you let go of a good but not great solution.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Life is messy, but sometimes great things come out of the mess (sticky note,…)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s a journey, make sure we enjoy ourselves while we’re on the way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;radical-collaboration&quot;&gt;Radical collaboration&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask for help.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Best ideas often come from others.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you reach ut to the world, the world reaches right back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 09:30:37 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/designing-your-life.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/designing-your-life.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>summary</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Overview of the recent DDoS Attacks (September/October 2016)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;##The Problem&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the spreading prevalence of embedded devices online (the “internet of things”), DDoS organisations discovered a new source of bots. 
Anti-DDoS providers are not prepared for the sudden enormous surge in data/bandwidth that can be directed towards their clients.
In other words: at the moment, the offense is better than the defense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##High profile cases&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;11/9: Krebs on security site was put offline by a DDoS attack twice the size of the biggest attack the anti-DDoS provider had ever seen (600+ GB/s).
Traffic was a mix of  SYN, GET, POST floods + a substantial % of traffic was spoofed GRE traffic (= unusual).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;23/9: OVH was the target of a DDoS attack. 1000GB/s!!
Traffic: unknown, probably identical as the Krebs attack.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;21/10: DynDNS was the target of a DDoS attack. DynDNS is the DNS provider for multiple sites. When it went down, its clients also were unreachable: reddit, twitter, paypal,…
Traffic: targeting the Authorative DNS infrastructure (DNS requests to random subdomains)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I understand it, the primary impact of this kind of attacks is on the available bandwidth of the provider.
With such large volumes reported, this becomes the first problem (as real clients cannot get to the resource due to congestion of the pipe). 
Of secondary importance is overwhelming of the service itself (application-level DDoS). 
When the upstream provider becomes able to filter out enough traffic, the attacks can change to target the application itself.
The bots are abundant enough to exhaust application resources, which will have the same effect from the end-user point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Characteristics of the botnet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The botnet is likely controlled by “Mirai”, software written to command and control mostly embedded devices. 
The source code of this software was leaked on the internet in September and contains functionality for the standard attacks described above.
At the time of writing, there are around 200k effected devices online (1.5 million affected devices in total), according to this &lt;a href=&quot;https://intel.malwaretech.com/botnet/mirai/?h=24&quot;&gt;tracker&lt;/a&gt;.
The botnet is comprised of: 96% IOT (almost all IP cameras made by a Chinese vendor), 4% home routers, less than 1% compromised Linux hosts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Mitigation
Providers are currently scrambling to add more capacity to their offerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, existing publications designed to limit spoofed IP traffic (a big enabler for most of these attacks) are being reconsidered. 
Top options are trying to filter ingress traffic (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bcp38.info/index.php/Main_Page&quot;&gt;BCP38&lt;/a&gt;) and source address validation (&lt;a href=&quot;https://lasr.cs.ucla.edu/adas/&quot;&gt;SAVE&lt;/a&gt;).
Implementing one of these would be a huge effort, requiring collaboration from a lot of actors on the internet and it remains to be seen how effective this countermeasures would be. (See &lt;a href=&quot;http://dyn.com/blog/recent-iot-based-attacks-what-is-the-impact-on-managed-dns-operators/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for a counter example).
In the case of attacks targeting DNS infrastructure, a promising option is &lt;a href=&quot;https://kb.isc.org/article/AA-01000/0/A-Quick-Introduction-to-Response-Rate-Limiting.html&quot;&gt;response-rate limiting&lt;/a&gt;. 
This mitigation allows a DNS server to drop requests when it sees a sudden surge in requests to a certain resource (with only very small variations).
Implementing this countermeasure would limit the impact on the attack that brought DynDNS to its knees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking down the bots (or preventing the control servers to take control) is also a massive undertaking.
Embedded devices have a historically bad record on security (often shipping with known holes) and patching (it’s extremely difficult to remove the holes once the devices are in the open).
Still, improving the security of these devices is the best long-term solution and will require effort from all of us in the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, your best bet is to have an anti-ddos provider and be in close contact with them. The best ones on the market are: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.akamai.com/us/en/resources/protect-against-ddos-attacks.jsp&quot;&gt;Akamai&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/ddos/&quot;&gt;CloudFlare&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.incapsula.com/ddos/&quot;&gt;Incapsula&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, make sure you drop all unwanted traffic as early as possible (at provider if possible, at your network edge,…)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 09:30:37 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/overview-iot-ddos.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/overview-iot-ddos.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>random</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Questions to consider when writing policies, processes or other documents</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The ability to write things down is something very human, it’s one of the things that separates us from animals.
Writing forces you to structure your thinking and approach a subject from different angles.
It is also one of the ways in which humans can scale: when you document an approach, you allow others to follow your approach and apply it for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to do just that, here are the questions I’m considering when writing new documentation. In no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###What is the goal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I actually want to achieve? This section should convince others the document is worth reading.
An additional advantage of explaining your goal is that you’re giving everyone a beacon they can work towards (and thus, making your goal a reality!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Who is the audience?
Think hard on how to approach the audience. Use their language and make sure to answer the question: “what’s in it for me?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###How will we reach the goal?
What will we do to achieve our objective?
I like to think about this myself first, before looking for answers elsewhere (see point below), an idea I picked up from “how to read a book”.
This forces me to think about potential solutions critically and assess strengths and weaknesses as well as completeness of the solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###Are there any reference frameworks I can leverage?
Only very seldom we’re trying to do something so new, there aren’t any reference frameworks yet..
In all other cases, reference frameworks allow you to build on the work of others. Personally, I find they often help me see the whole picture and often provide surprising insight into the relative importance of sub-areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###How is my part connected with the rest of the organisation?
You’re never on an island. Check what you’re doing and find out where you’re interacting with others. Then go ask those people what information they can deliver or what they’ll do with the information you’ll provide for them. Determine if they can deliver what you need and if you can provide what they need. Then agree on how and when the information will be exchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###How will I measure what I want to achieve (KPI’s)?
What gets measured, gets improved. Think very hard on what you want measured, because once people realise a number is important, they will make it go up (using the shortest available route). It’s very easy to improve the wrong thing.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 10:30:37 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>/writing-documents.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/writing-documents.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>random</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>It's 2016 and I still managed to have a unicode issue</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you ever run into an issue that looks related to unicode/utf (you get characters such as “\00eb”), check if it’s installed on your system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently was stumped by this, because my sinatra/ruby application worked on my dev machine, but not on the server (I’ve heard that one before! ;-) ).
Turns out utf wasn’t installed on the server (a debian machine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For future reference, it’s easy to install:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;append &lt;em&gt;en_US UTF-8&lt;/em&gt; to /etc/locale.gen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;run “locale-gen” as root&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(optional) export this variable in your terminal &lt;em&gt;export LANG=en_US.UTF-8&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the environment variable available for apache/passenger/ruby. You do this by putting &lt;em&gt;SetEnv LANG en_US.UTF-8&lt;/em&gt; in the appropriate vhost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 09:30:37 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>/its-2015-and-i-still-had-a-unicode-issue.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/its-2015-and-i-still-had-a-unicode-issue.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>summary</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
